# Aseem Srivastava PhD Scholar at LCS2 Lab, IIIT Delhi, India

☑ as3eem.github.io ② aseems@iiitd.ac.in

A fifth-year PhD student at IIIT Delhi, currently under the guidance of Dr. Md. Shad Akhtar and Dr. Tanmoy Chakraborty at LCS2 Lab, India. My research interest is in NLP/Deep Learning for Dialogue Systems, with a specialized focus on improvising conversational mental health assistants. I specialize in applying large language models (LLMs) and LLMOps for dialogue and behavioral understanding and encourage open sourcing with production-ready research.

# Education

## INDRAPRASTHA INSTITUTE OF INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY (IIIT DELHI), DELHI

2020 - PRESENT

PhD in Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) | CGPA: 8.5

Thesis: Building Blocks of Dialogue System for Effective Virtual Mental Health Assistants

Supervisor: Dr. Md. Shad Akhtar & Dr. Tanmoy Chakraborty

#### KAMLA NEHRU INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY (KNIT), SULTANPUR

2016 - 2020

B.Tech in Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) | Agg: 68.3%

Thesis: Amazon Review Analysis to Guage User Sentiments

# **Publications**

#### EMNLP (Main)

Knowledge Planning in Large Language Models for Domain-Aligned Counseling Summarization

Aseem Srivastava, Smriti Joshi, Tanmoy Chakraborty, Md Shad Akhtar

LLM Controlled Generation Knowledge Infusion

#### JMIR MH

## Exploring the Efficacy of LLMs in Summarizing Counseling Sessions: A Benchmark Study

2024

2024

Prottay Kumar Adhikary, Aseem Srivastava, Shivani Kumar, Salam Michael Singh, Puneet Manuja, Jini K Gopinath, Vijay Krishnan, Swati Kedia, Koushik Sinha Deb, Tanmoy Chakraborty

[LLM] GenerativeAl

# The Web Conf

# Response-act Guided Reinforced Dialogue Generation for Mental Health Counseling

2023

Aseem Srivastava, Ishan Pandey, Md. Shad Akhtar, Tanmoy Chakraborty

Transformer Reinforcement Learning | GenerativeAl | Controlled Generation |

#### KDD 2022

# Counseling Summarization using Mental Health Knowledge Guided Utterance Filtering

Aseem Srivastava, Tharun Suresh, Grin Lord, Md. Shad Akhtar, Tanmoy Chakraborty

 LLM
 Knowledge Infusion
 Controlled Generation

## ICWSM 2022

# A Computational Approach to Understand Mental Health from Reddit : Knowledge-aware Multitask Learning Framework

Usha Lokala, Aseem Srivastava, Triyasha Ghosh Dastidar, Tanmoy Chakraborty, Md Shad Akthar, Maryam Panahiazar, Amit Sheth

Transformers | Reddit Mental Health | Knowledge Infusion

#### WSDM 2022

# Speaker and Time-aware Joint Contextual Learning for Dialogue-act Classification in Counselling Conversations

Ganeshan Malhotra, Abdul Waheed, Aseem Srivastava, Md. Shad Akhtar, Tanmoy Chakraborty

Transformers Joint Learning

## **Under Review**

- > Knowledge-infused Hierarchy-aware Emotion Recognition in Code-mixed Conversations
- > Sentiment-guided Commonsense-aware Response Generation for Counseling
- > Critical Behavioral Traits Foster Peer Engagement in Online Reddit Communities

# **Skills**

Interests NLP - Dialogue Systems, Deep Learning, Machine Learning, Human Behavior, GenAl, LLMs

**Technical** Data Structures and Algorithms, Python, PyTorch, LLMOps, Tensorflow, Git, Cloud Services

Web & Android NodeJS, Flutter, MySQL, NoSQL

# Experience

RESEARCH INTERN AUGUST 2022 - JANUARY 2023

Mpathic | USA (Remote)

Undertook research statement around NLP and dialogue summarization tailored for counseling. I led the development of an end-to-end pipeline, crafting a novel methodology from scratch and overseeing its implementation for in-house deployment, including optimizing team workflows. Our research findings were published at KDD 2022 (A\* conference).

LLMs AWS

Data Science Intern

July 2019 - August 2019

Analytics Vidhya | Gurgaon, India

Spearheaded the development of machine learning and deep learning models for an in-house portal. In addition, we worked with a team to enhance our understanding of deep neural networks to facilitate better recommendation frameworks.

Machine Learning Deep Learning Text Analytics

# Organized Tutorials & Workshops

ICON 2023

Building Blocks of AI-Driven Mental Health Counseling

(Tutorial)

Organizers: Aseem Srivastava, Neeraj, Yash Kumar Atri, Shivani Kumar, Shad Akhtar, Tanmoy Chakraborty

# **Invited Talks & Symposiums**

# [Symposiums]

> Google Research Week 2023 & 2024 – Got two back to back invitations to attend and present our work at Research Week with Google, India.

## [Talks]

- > ACM ARCS 2024 Got invited by ACM India to present a lightning talk and our work on dialogue response generation in NISER Bhubhneshwar.
- > Cord.Al 2023 Got invited to present a talk on Role of Conversational Agent's Component in Digital Counseling.

# Position of Responsibility

- 2024 Serving as Program Committee member at ASONAM 2024, Italy.
- Leading an open-source community of 500+ like-minded enthusiasts to encourage awareness and know-ledge of Deep Learning for NLP.
- 2022 Served as Web Chair at International Conference on Natural Language Processing (ICON) 2022, India.
- 2022 Served as Web Chair at CONSTRAINT Workshop (co-located w/ ACL 2022).
- 2021 Served as a volunteer at notable conferences, including KDD, ACL, AAAI, COLING, and WSDM.

## **Achievements**

- 2023 Received Google Research Grant to present our WWW '23 paper in Austin, USA.
- 2022 Received ACM India Grant to present our KDD '22 paper in Washington DC, USA.
- 2019 Placed in the top 9% (N=8000) of the leaderboard in IIT-M Alumni Association Hackearth's machine learning challenge with an accuracy of 99.63%.
- 2018 Runners up in Facebook's Digital Hackathon for creating an social web platform and won INR 40,000.

# References

Dr. Md. Shad Akhtar

Assistant Professor, IIIT Delhi (shad.akhtar@iiitd.ac.in)

Dr. Tanmoy Chakraborty

Associate Professor, IIT Delhi (chak.tanmoy.iit@gmail.com)